<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetextract" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Extracts portions of an existing Control Network
  </brief>

  <description>
    Extracts Control Points into a new Control Network from a specified Control
    Network in accordance to specified filters.

    A results group will be recorded, including the Control Points removed
    during extraction, as well as all of the Control Points which had Control
    Measures removed from them.

    In addition, Control Points extracted as well as a summary of the results
    group are both included in the record.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-07-22">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-07-31">
      Refactored for readability, added parameter defaults, and added detail to
      the application log.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-11">
      Added an additional output progress bar.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-21">
      Added the points kept to the print file.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-28">
      Fixed TOLIST blank lines, added the POINTLIST option, and changed the
      CUBEPOINTS parameter to take a filename instead of a boolean.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Input Files">

      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>List of ISIS3 input cubes in the Control Network</brief>
          <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS3 cube file names. Every file
          used in the match point file should be represented in this list.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.list
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CNET">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>Isis3 input Control Network file</brief>
          <description>
            Use this parameter to specify the control network file to extract
            the OUTNET from.
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net
          </filter>
        </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output">

      <parameter name="TOLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>List of ISIS3 output cubes</brief>
          <description>
          This text file contains one column of ISIS3 cube file names associated
          with the OUTNET. This list can only include cubes that were privided
          in the FROMLIST.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.list
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="OUTNET">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>Isis3 output Control Network file</brief>
          <description>
            The resultant Control Network extracted from CNET.
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net
          </filter>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>Parent Network Id</internalDefault>
        <brief>
            Name of the extracted Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
            The ID or name of the extracted Control Network. This string should
            be unique.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>cnetextracted</item></default>
        <brief>
            The description of the extracted network.
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string describing purpose of this extracted control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Filters">

      <parameter name="NOIGNORE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Remove ignored points when extracting the Control Net</brief>
        <description>
          When true, all ignored Control Points and all ignored Control
          Measures provided by the Control Net will be removed.

          The keywords IgnoredPoints and IgnoredMeasures will be logged when
          using this option. They depict which Control Points and Control Measures
          were not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOHELD">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Remove held points when extracting the Control Net</brief>
        <description>
          When true, all held Control Points in the Control Net will be
          removed.

          The keyword HeldPoints will be logged when using this option. Each
          Control Point it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOSINGLEMEASURE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Remove Control Points with one Control Measure</brief>
        <description>
  	       When true, all Control Points that are reduced to zero or one Control
           Measure (from other selected filters) will not be included in the
           output Control Network.

          The keyword SingleMeasurePoints will be logged when using this option. Each
          Control Point it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>REFERENCE</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="REFERENCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Extract reference Control Measures</brief>
        <description>
          When true, only reference Control Measures will be extracted into the
          output Control Net. This option cannot be used in conjunction with the
          NOSINGLEMEASURE option since there is only a single reference
          measure in any Control Point.

          The keyword NonReferenceMeasures will be logged when using this option.
          Each Control Measure it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>NOSINGLEMEASURE</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CUBEPOINTS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Extract Control Points containing these input cube</brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename which contains a list of
          cubes. All the Control Points which contain at least on of these
          cubes will be extracted.

          The keyword NonCubePoints will be logged when using this option.
          Each Control Point it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
        <inclusions>
          <item>CUBEMEASURES</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="CUBEMEASURES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Extract Control Measures containing an input cube</brief>
        <description>
          When true, remove all Control Measures from extracted Control Points
          which do not contain a cube from the CUBEPOINTS list.
          This option can only be used when a file has been provided for
          CUBEPOINTS.

          The keyword NonCubeMeasures will be logged when using this option.
          Each Control Measure it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTLIST">
       <type>filename</type>
       <fileMode>input</fileMode>
       <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
       <brief>File containing Control Point Ids which will be extracted</brief>
       <description>
         Use this parameter to select the filename which contains a list of
        point ids. All the Control Points with matching Ids will be extracted
        as long as another seleted filter does not exclude the Control Point.

        The keyword NonListedPoints will be logged when using this option.
        Each Control Point it contains was not extracted due to this filter.
       </description>
       <filter>
         *.lis
       </filter>
     </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATLON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Extract Control Points in the lat/lon range</brief>
        <description>
  	       When true, all Control Points that are outside of the provided
           latitude longitude range will be removed. Control Points whos
           latitude longitude cannot be computed will be removed.

           Ground Points will use the lat/lon values provided in the CNET while
           Tie Points will calculate their lat/lon from the images provided by
           the FROMLIST.  These calculated lat/lon values will be added to Tie
           Point in the OUTNET for reference purposes. No Isis application will
           use these added Control Point keywords.

          The keywords LatLonOutOfRange and NoLatLonPoints will be logged when
          using this option. Each Control Point they contain were not extracted
          due to this filter, were LatLonOutOfRange is the Control Points who
          did not fall within the provided range, and NoLatLonPoints were the
          Control Points for which a Latitude and Longitude could not be
          determined.

           Note: This option is expensive.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>MINLAT</item>
          <item>MAXLAT</item>
          <item>MINLON</item>
          <item>MAXLON</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>-90.0</item></default>
        <brief>Minimum Control Point Latitude</brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a latitude less than LATMIN will be removed.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>90.0</item></default>
        <brief>Maximum Control Point Latitude</brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a latitude greater than LATMAX will be removed.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
        <brief>Minimum Control Point Longitude</brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a longitude less than LONMIN will be removed.

           If MINLON is greater than MAXLON than the latitude range is assumed
           to cross the 0/360 latitude boundry, where points with latitudes greater
           than MINLON or less than MAXLON will be included.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>360.0</item></default>
        <brief>Maximum Control Point Longitude</brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a longitude greater than LONMAX will be removed.

           If MAXLON is less than MINLON than the latitude range is assumed
           to cross the 0/360 latitude boundry, where points with latitudes greater
           than MINLON or less than MAXLON will be included.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
