<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="overlapstats" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Calculates the statistics of overlapping cube regions</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    Taking a list of cubes and an image overlap list file from 
    "findimageoverlaps", this application determines the statistics on all 
    overlapping polygons of those provided images, and displays those values 
    in a table as depicted below.  Note that the units of Thichness is done in 
    number of images, Area is done in square meters, and SN Count is also done 
    in number of images.
    </p>
    <br />
    <table border="0" cellpadding="9">
      <tr>
        <td></td>
        <td>Thickness</td>
        <td>Area</td>
        <td>SN Count</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Minimum</td>
        <td>[The minimum thickness of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The minimum area of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The smallest number of Serial Numbers used in any overlapping polygon]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Maximum</td>
        <td>[The maximum thickness of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The maximum area of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The largest number of Serial Numbers used in any overlapping polygon]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Average</td>
        <td>[The average thickness of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The average area of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The average count of Serial Numbers used in all overlapping polygon]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>StandardDeviation</td>
        <td>[The standard deviation of the thicknesses of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The standard deviation of the areas of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The standard deviation of the Serial Number counts of all overlapping polygons]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Variance</td>
        <td>[The variance of the thicknesses of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The variance of the areas of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The variance of the Serial Number counts of all overlapping polygons]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Sum</td>
        <td>[The sum of the thicknesses of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The sum of the areas of all overlapping polygons]</td>
        <td>[The sum of the Serial Number counts of all overlapping polygons]</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <br />
    <p>
    In addition, if there are any cubes within the list that do not overlap with
    any other cube in the list, a second table is provided, which merely
    consists of those cube's filenames and Serial Numbers.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Math and Statistics</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

   <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-09-30">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-10-28">
      Fixed the formatting for a  tab tabletype, improved documentation, and
      added an example.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-11-10">
      The output file (TO) must now be specified.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-17">
      Added support for image overlap files, which is what "OVERLAPLIST" needs to
      be. This is a required parameter obtained from running "findimageoverlaps."
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-10-28">
      Added error throwing when there are no overlaps among the cubes provided
      and other small bug fixes.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of Input cubes
        </brief>
        <description>
          The filename which contains a list of input cubes.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERLAPLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          This is the list of image overlaps corresponding to this control net
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename which contains the
          overlap list. You can obtain this file by running "findimageoverlaps."
        </description>
        <filter>
          *
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output stats file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The table file of the resultant stats.  If any outlying cubes are
          found, they will be listed in a second table.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TABLETYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>TAB</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Output data format</brief>
        <description>
          The resultant statistics of the overlapping cubes will be formatted
          in a table according to the following option.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="TAB">
            <brief> Tab Table </brief>
            <description>
              Places the resulting statistics into an easy to read table,
              which displays values seperates by tabs.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="CSV">
            <brief>CSV</brief>
            <description>
              Output the resulting statistics into Comma Seperated Value (CSV)
              format with values in scientific notation and a precision of 15.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>

  <examples>

    <example>
      <brief>Overlapping Statistics</brief>
      <description>
        Get the overlapping statistics of the following cubes.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>  from=cubes.lis tabletype=tab to=stats.txt</commandLine>
        <description>
        In this example overlapstats will calculate the statistics of the thickness,
        area, and serial number count of the overlapping polygons that the cubes
        provided in cubes.lis create, and output those results into an easy to
        read table named stats.txt
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/cubes.lis">
          <brief>The list of cubes to use</brief>
          <description>
            This is the input list of cubes to use to create the overlap which
            the statistics will be ran on.
          </description>
          <parameterName>FROMLIST</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/stats.txt">
          <brief>The resultant stats</brief>
          <description>
            This is the file containing the stats of overlapstats.  Note: if
            you leave the TO parameter empty, the stats will be displayed
            instead of being placed in a file.
          </description>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/cube.1.jpg" width="494" height="494">
          <brief>First image</brief>
          <description>This is the first input image for the overlapstats to use
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="cube.1.cube" src="assets/thumb/thumb.1.jpg" width="198" height="198"/>
        </image>
        <image src="assets/image/cube.2.jpg" width="493" height="493">
          <brief>Second image</brief>
          <description>This is the second input image
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="cube.2.cub" src="assets/thumb/thumb.2.jpg" width="198" height="198"/>
        </image>
        <image src="assets/image/cube.3.jpg" width="481" height="476">
          <brief>Third image</brief>
          <description>This is the third input image
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" cube.3.cub" src="assets/thumb/thumb.3.jpg" width="198" height="197"/>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

    </example>

  </examples>

</application>
