<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hipical" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Performs calibration on a HiRISE cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will calibrate a HiRISE cube applying a gain (multiplied) 
    and/or offset (subtracted) matrix.  The program applies the entered
    or default matrix cube(s) and selects the band to apply based on the
    ccd and channel.  If no value for MATRIX is entered, the default
    matrix cube(s) are used.   The file specification for the default(s) are
    based on the FROM cube label values for tdi and bin and the directory
    used is $mro/calibration.  A single line (all samples) is read from the
    matrix file and applied to each line in the input cube.  The following
    equations are used:

    <pre>
    GAIN:      out = from * A-matrix
    OFFSET: out = from - B-matrix
    BOTH:     out = from * A-matrix -  B-matrix
    </pre>

    The FROM cube must have the same number of samples as the MATRIX
    cube.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2006-08-22">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2006-09-19">
       Changed user inputs.
     </change>
    <change name="Deborah Lee Soltesz" date="2006-11-13" hidden="true">
      Fixed typo.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

   <category>
      <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>
  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>ratio</item>
      <item>poly</item>
      <item>algebra</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the HiRISE single-band cube to be calibrated
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATRIX">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Matrix cube
         </brief>
         <internalDefault>
             None
         </internalDefault>
         <description>
           This file should be a 28-band cube where each band contains the gain or offsets corresponding to the 
           samples in the input cube.  Each band should contain a single line that will be applied to every line of the
           input cube as specified by the selected option.  

           If no value is entered the default matrix file(s) will be read from the directory $mro/calibration.  The filename(s)
           are built based on the value of OPTION and the ccd and channel keyword values read from the FROM cube.
           The A-matrix cube will have the form A_matrix_tdi##_bin#.cub and the B-matrix cube will have the form
           B_matrix_tdi##_bin#.cub, where ## is replaced by the tdi number and # is replaced by the bin number.

           The application will select the band to apply based on the ccd and the channel keyword values read from the
           labels of the FROM cube.  The number of samples in this cube must match the number of samples in the input cube.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the resulting  calibrated cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Option">
      <parameter name="OPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>GAIN</item></default>
        <brief>
          Calibration mode option
        </brief>
        <description>
          Select the calibration mode to be performed on the input cube.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="GAIN">
            <brief>Multiply the A-matrix</brief>
            <description>
              Multiply each sample value in each line of the input cube by the corresponding sample value in the A-matrix
              cube band that matches the tdi/bin/ccd/channel of the input cube, FROM.   Apply the following equation:
                out = A * from
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="OFFSET">
            <brief>Subtract the B-matrix</brief>
            <description>
             Subtract each sample value in the B-matrix band corresponding to the tdi/bin/ccd/channel of the input cube, 
             from each corresponding sample in every line of the input cube.  Offset the input cube (from) using the
             following equation:
		        out = from - B
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BOTH">
            <brief>Both gain and offset</brief>
            <description>
              Apply the both the offset (subtract the B-matrix line) and the gain (multiply A-matrix line) to each line in
              FROM using the following equation:
                out = (from  - B) * A
              The default matrix files must be used in this option (see MATRIX or program help for more information on
              the defaults).
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
