<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hiclean2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Cleans a HiRISE image using Alan Delamere's's clean_image application
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
        <b>hiclean2</b> implements Alan Delamere's version of HiRISE image radiometric calibration
        as coded in his IDL program called <i>clean.pro</i>.  Mike's general approach is to 
        use the calibration data acquired for each image and compute statistics from it used to
        characterize instrument conditions at the time the image is acquired.  This data includes
        the reverse clock, mask, buffer and dark current data that is stored in Isis objects within
        all HiRISE Isis cubes.  These objects are sometimes referred to as Binary Large OBjects,
      </p>
      <p>
        Excerpts from Alan's description of his algorithm:
        <PRE>
Cimage_mask,image,info
Step 1. Average all the usable masked pixels in each column including buffer and
 dark for the 18 binned lines for bin 1, 9 lines for bin 2 and 4 lines for bin 4
. Floating point array of 1052 columns for bin 1, 540 columns for bin 2 and 284 
columns for bin 4.
Step 2. Subtract this line from every line in the image.

Cimage_dark, image, info
The dark region has had subtracted from it the dark current generated in the mas
k area by the above procedure. It should be a nominal zero value except for drif
t and temperature change during imaging
Step 1. Average the last twelve columns of each line and produce a floating poin
t array of n lines long.
Step 2. Apply an 11 point smoothing to this dark array. [I have tried a number o
f different smoothing approaches including using median and averaging of differe
nt lengths. For the recent dark images the 11 point smoothing produced the minim
um observable degradation.]
Step 3. Subtract the smoothed value from each line in the array.

The actual code used is given below.

What are the residual errors from this method?
1.      The masked area pixels are closer to the hot amplifier than the image pi
xels. The temperature of the CCD will rise during imaging so insufficient dark c
urrent may not be removed.
2.      There is an unexplained negative value in the binned area prior to the d
ark area. This is the biggest error. For bin 2 it is about 15-30 DN.
3.      Other?

Essential algorithm extracted from code below
  ave_lines,image,21,20+maskbinend,masked       ;All columns in masked
for I = 0L,nlines-1 do a(0,i)=image(*,i)-masked         ;all columns have masked
 subtracted
ave_cols,image,nc-12,nc-1,dark
dark   = smooth(dark,11)
for i  = 0L,nlines-1 do a(12:(nc-17),i)  = image(12:(nc-17),i)-dark(i)*bin
;Note bin not bin^2
for i  = 0L,nlines-1 do a(0:12,i)  = image(0:12,i)-dark(i)
for i  = 0L,nlines-1 do a(nc-16:nc-1,i)  = image(nc-16:nc-1,i)-dark(i)
        </PRE>
      </p>
      <p>
          In addition to those changes, some consideration has been given to
          situations where bad missing (null) data exists in the mask and dark
          calibration data.  Bad data could occur in these areas when gaps
          occur in the dowlink of the file from the spacecraft or other anomolies.
          Also, LookUp Tables (LUTs) can cause data saturation if they are
          not carefully considered prior to use. 
      </p>
      <p>
          In cases of missing data in the mask region, the minimum and maximum
          of the data after averaging each column is computed.  For low saturated
          and null special pixels, the minimum mask average value is used.  For high
          saturation special pixels, the maximum is used.
      </p>
      <p>
          For the dark pixel calibration data, an 11 pixel wide filter is applied after
          averaging each line in this region.  This replaces any missing data with
          the average of the 11 pixel filter.  If data is wider than 11 pixels in this
          data, nulling of image data will result.
      </p>
      <p>
          Under any condition valid data is nulled due to insufficent calibration data
          in either region, hiclean2 terminates with and error.  The resulting output
          files is retained, however - just in case it is useable.
      </p>
  </description>
  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2005-12-19">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-02-19">
        Discovered an off-by-one index issue when computing drift
        correction. It amounted to approximately 2 DN difference.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-03-14">
        Changed to use the median statistic for computations involving
        calibration.  The average is still used to gather quantitative
        data on the radiometric calibration process.
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-06-21">
      Modified the cleaning sequence and added the propagation of 
      the cleaned blobs
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-08-04">
        There was a bug in how the line-by-line cleaning was being performed.
        Basically, drift correction for all lines were done using dark and buffer
        statistics from the first line.  Also, the 100 line filter was not being used
        in the drift correction.  These problems have been fix.  This fix has also
        nearly halved the processing time.

        Image statistics are now added to the Application log file instead of
        standard output.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-10-26">
        This version is a nearly complete rewrite based upon a simplified
        version of an Alan Delamere algorithm.   

        It also targets bloody IR10_1 and avoids using the last 2000 lines
        or so of calibration data, propagating the last occuring dark current
        drift.

        Furthermore, it will terminate with an error if any valid data is NULLed
        due to bad calibration, which can occur in gaps or bad LUTing.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-11-06">
        Not enough lines in IR10_1 were being ignored in the dark current drift
        corection.  Changed 2000 to 3100.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-11-22">
        Separately count nulls induced through mask and dark correction and
        report them to user and add to labels.  Also throws a Math error when
        either of these counts are not zero.   This can be detected when the
        exit status is 9.  The ouput TO image is retained for further use when
        this condition is raised so decisions can be made as to its usefulness.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-01-18">
        Modified hiclean such that binning factor is no longer applied to drift
        correction.  Also,  the smoothing filter of the drift is independantly
        applied on the Calibration and Image buffer regions.    This version
        is now known as hiclean2.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-02-22">
        Add the DARKOPT option that allows user to select how dark correction
        is handled.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2007-06-05">
        Modified to work with iString/StringTools merge
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-09-28">
        Will no longer abort with an error when missing data is in the
        (dark pixel) calibration region.  It still prints a message to report
        this condition.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to calibrate
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
            The name of the cube to which the cleaning operation is to  be
            applied.  Note that although it is possible to take the ancillary
            data from one file, compute the statistics from it, and apply it
            another, this is currently not supported.
            </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
	      Use this parameter to specify the name of the output cube.
          If you do not include an extension of ".cub" it will be added 
	      automatically.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CLEANSTATS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Produce output of statistics generated for the cleaning operation
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                The contents of this file will contain all the statistics generated
                for the cleaning process.  This includes mask pixels and dark
                buffer calibration data applied to the image data.
             </p>
             <p>
                Below is a partial listing of what is being written to the
                output file:
            </p>
            <PRE>
Group = ImageStatistics
  File          = TRA_000865_1905_BG12_0.cub
  Lines         = 2500Group = ImageStatistics
  File          = TRA_000865_1905_BG12_0.cub
  Lines         = 2500
  Samples       = 256
  MaskAverage   = 1072.7843309859
  MaskStdDev    = 44.159718656799
  BadMaskPixels = 0
  DarkAverage   = 17.311132445657
  DarkStdDev    = 6.9278509333753
  BadDarkPixels = 0
End_Group

Group = CalibrationStatistics
  Binning           = 4
  TDI               = 32
  CPMM              = 4
  Channel           = 0
  FirstImageSample  = 12
  FirstImageLine    = 33
  FirstBufferSample = 0
  FirstDarkSample   = 268
End_Group
End

*** Dark and Mask Correction Buffers ***
       Row      Dark    Column      Mask
       -33  -9.69508       -12      1110
       -32   -9.9678       -11      1041
       -31  -9.83144       -10      1050
       -30  -9.83144        -9      1050
       -29   -9.9678        -8    1054.5
       -28  -10.1042        -7      1059
       -27  -9.83144        -6      1076
       -26  -9.83144        -5   1063.25
       -25  -10.1042        -4      1059
       -24  -9.69508        -3      1059
       -23  -9.28598        -2      1076
       -22  -9.28598        -1      1059
       -21  -9.28598         0    968.25
       -20  -9.14962         1      1050
       -19  -8.87689         2    1084.5
       -18  -8.60417         3   1114.75
          .        .                   .          .
          .        .                   .          .
          .        .                   .          .
            </PRE>
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DARKOPT">
          <type>string</type>
          <default><item>DERIVED</item></default>
          <brief>Specifies how dark current correction is applied</brief>
          <description>
              The HiRISE dark current is computed from the dark image pixels
              collected during image aquisition.  An algorithm which averages
              the last 12 dark values in each line and then runs an 11 line
              width smoothing algorithm is appled to each image line to correct
              for dark current.  This works fine under most conditions, however
              there are remains problematic images that it introduces horizontal
              streaks.  This option allows the user to use this algorithm (default),
              the median of all dark values from the aforementioned algorithm, or
              skip it entirely (essentially setting the dark correction to 0).
          </description>
          <list>
             <option value="DERIVED">
                 <brief>Apply the derived dark current based upon algorithm</brief>
                 <description>
                     This option applies the dark current correction algorithm which derives the
                     appropriate dark current offset from data collected during image
                     acquisition.  This is the default.
                 </description>
             </option>
             <option value="MEDIAN">
                 <brief>Apply median dark current value</brief>
                 <description> 
                     This option computes the median value resulting from all
                     the line dark current corrections and subtracts this value
                     from all lines.
                 </description>
             </option>
             <option value="NONE">
                 <brief>Do not correct for dark current</brief>
                 <description> 
                     Selecting this option essentially sets the dark current
                     subtraction to 0.  Using this option will do no dark current
                     correction to the image data.
                 </description>
             </option>
          </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
