<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mat2cnet" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Converts an Isis2 match point file to an Isis3 control network file.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program converts an Isis2 match point file to an Isis3 control
      network file.  It requires a list file of Isis 2 cubes and corresponding 
      list file of Isis 3 cubes , a match point file, a output pvl name, a 
      network ID, a target and a description.  It also takes, as an optional 
      input, a rand file containing latitude, longitude and radius for each 
      corresponding point ID. 
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2007-08-10">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-12-14">
      Now IMAGE_NUMBER will be used before IMAGE_ID for matching files
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2008-04-15"> 
        Fixed bug where serial numbers were not correct.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-19"> 
        Error message added for missing FSC's
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-01">
       Added exception message when the given MATCH file's "Matchpoint total"
       keyword is less than the number of actual Match Points in the file.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-11-06">
       Added RAND input parameter and updated documentation.  Added exception 
       messages for invalid match point file headers and values. Added 1%
       Progress updates to show potentially slower steps. Added appTests for
       RAND parameter and to catch errors.  Added examples to xml file.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-12-17">
       Modify code to allow use of particular types of edited RAND files. 
       Updated description of RAND parameter to reflect this change.  
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Isis 2 Files">
      <parameter name="LIST2">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of Isis2 input cubes in the match point file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing one column of Isis 2 cube file names. Every 
          file used in the match point file should be represented in this list. 
          The cubes must be available for the program to open and must be in the 
          same order as the Isis 3 cubes in LIST3.  An error will be thrown if 
          the number of files in this list does not match the number of files in 
          LIST2, or if the IMAGE_ID and IMAGE_NUMBER keywords are not found in 
          any Isis 2 cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.txt *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
            Isis2 match point file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the Isis2 match point file to be
          converted to an Isis3 control network file.  This file must contain a 
          two line header.  The first line of the header must have the 
          "Matchpoint Total" keyword and a value for the number of measures in 
          the match point file.  The second line of the header should be text 
          labels for each column.  The match point file has 7 columns: PointID, 
          FSC, LINE, SAMP, CLASS, DIAMETER, and Comments.  The Point ID is 
          made up of alphanumeric characters,  FSC is an integer, LINE and SAMP 
          must be doubles.  CLASS is used to determine the measure type.  Valid 
          values include T (set to reference measure, validated manual), M 
          (validated manual), S (validated automatic), or U (if line/samp=0/0, 
          set unmeasured, otherwise set estimated).   The DIAMETER column is 
          used in the case of a crater.  Comments are not read in to this 
          application. A match point file may only have one line for a 
          particular PointID/FSC combination, otherwise an error will be thrown 
          since there is no way to determine which line contains correct values.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.mat *.txt *.dat *.tbl
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="RAND">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
            RAND file containing latitude, longitude, and radius values for 
            given Point IDs.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the RAND file to assign latitude,
          longitude and radius values associated with corresponding 
          point IDs in the match file.  These files do not contain headers and 
          have 4 unlabeled columns: LATITUDE, LONGITUDE, RADIUS, and PointID.  
          The lines of original RAND files have exactly 79 characters, and
          columns are right justified with specific lengths, namely, 24, 24, 24,
          and 7.  The only edited RAND files that are valid for this program are 
          those that have a single space added between the RADIUS and the 
          PointID. LATITUDE, LONGITUDE, and RADIUS values must be doubles and
          PointID is alphanumeric.  If this file contains a Point ID that does
          not exist in the match point file, it will be added to the ControlNet
          output as a "Tie" point with no measures.  The user may remove these,
          if necessary, using the
                                  <strong>qnet</strong> application.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ppp *.dat *.txt
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>
          None
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Isis 3 Files">
        <parameter name="LIST3">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
            List of Isis3 input cubes in the match point file.
          </brief>
          <description>
          A text file containing one column of Isis 3 cube file names. Every 
          file used in the match point file should be represented in this list. 
          The cubes must be available for the program to open and must be in the 
          same order as the Isis 2 cubes in LIST2.  An error will be thrown if 
          the number of files in this list does not match the number of files in 
          LIST2.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.lis *.txt *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CONTROL">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
              Isis3 output control network file
          </brief>
          <description>
            Use this parameter to specify the file name of the output Isis3
            control network.
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net *.pvl *.ctl *.cnet
          </filter>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Control">
    <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
      <type>string</type>
      <brief>
          The description of this output control network.
      </brief>
      <description>
          A string describing this control network.
      </description>
    </parameter>

      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            Name of the output control network
        </brief>
        <description>
            The ID or name of this particular control network. This string
            should be unique.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TARGET">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            The target body of the control network.
        </brief>
        <description>
            The targeted planet or body for the control points and measures in 
            this control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Create control net from match point file</brief>
      <description>
        This example demonstrates how to use the  <strong>mat2cnet </strong> 
        application to create a control network from a match point file.  In 
        this case, no RAND file is used.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          list2=../IN/isis2cubes.lis match=../IN/matchpointfile.mat 
          list3=../IN/isis3cubes.lis control=../OUT/controlnet.net 
          description="Default Test Network" networkid= TestNet01 target=Titan
        </commandLine>
        <description> 
          Run the <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application to create a ControlNet 
          file from a match point file with corresponding Isis2 cubelist and 
          Isis3 cubelist
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="496" height="550" src="assets/images/mat2cnetGuiEx1.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the 
              <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application.  The RAND parameter is left
              as the default of "None".
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="180" height="200" caption="Mat2cnet Gui using match point file" src="assets/thumbs/mat2cnetGuiThumbEx1.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/match.mat">
          <brief>Example of match point file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid match point file with proper
            header and columns.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            MATCH
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/controlnet.net">
          <brief>Example of control net file.</brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file is an example of the output control network created
            from the given match point file.  Notice the NetworkId, TargetName,
            and Description are assigned the values from the command line.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CONTROL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Create control net from match point file and RAND file</brief>
      <description>
        This example demonstrates how to use the  <strong>mat2cnet </strong> 
        application to create a control network from a match point file and 
        corresponding RAND file.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          list2=../IN/isis2cubes.lis match=../IN/matchpt.mat rand=../IN/rand.ppp
          list3=../IN/isis3cubes.lis control=../OUT/control.net
          description="Rand Test Network" networkid= TestNet02 target=Titan
        </commandLine>
        <description> 
          Run the <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application to create a ControlNet 
          file from a match point file with corresponding Isis2 cubelist, Isis3
          cubelist, and RAND file.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="691" height="550" src="assets/images/mat2cnetGuiEx2.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the 
              <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application with a RAND file.  
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="159" caption="Mat2cnet Gui using intensity" src="assets/thumbs/mat2cnetGuiThumbEx2.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/match.mat">
          <brief>Example of match point file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid match point file with proper
            header and columns.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            MATCH
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/rand.ppp">
          <brief>Example of RAND file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid RAND file.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            RAND
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/controlnet_rand.net">
          <brief>Example of control net file.</brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file is an example of the output control network created
            from the given match point file and RAND file.  Notice the 
            NetworkId, TargetName, and Description are assigned the values from 
            the command line.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CONTROL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
