<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qnet" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create and edit control networks
  </brief>

  <description>
     <p>
      <div style="background-color:gold; border:2pxsolidred; fort-weight:bold;">
        This program is a prototype version and may contain errors.  
        Please do not report errors. The documentation is not complete and may
        be inaccurate. USE AT YOUR OWN RISK.
      </div>
    </p>
    <p>
   This program will create and edit control networks. 
    </p>
    <p>
    To run qnet, you will need to create a text file containing a list of all cubes in the control network.
    </p>
    <p>
    The main window of qnet is similar to the program "qview".  You will see many of the same tools
    such as zoom, pan, stretch, etc.  The Tie tool will be the default tool selected (the bottom button along
    the right hand toolbar) when qnet is launched.
    </p>
    <p>
    Once qnet is up, select the "Open network" button or the open action (from File menu), and open the file
    containing the list of cubes in the network.  You will then be prompted for the
    control network file.  If you are editing an existing one, choose that file.  If you are
    creating a new control network, choose the "Cancel" button.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Control Network Navigator allows you to filter cubes or points on different attributes.   If filtering cubes,
      you can then view the cube(s) chosen from the filtered list.  If filtering points, you can view the cube(s) for 
      the chosen points from the list or edit a chosen point.
    </p>
    <p>
    Cubes are displayed in the main window, with control points displayed as green "+", 
    yellow "+" (points set to "Ignored") or red "+" (point currently being edited).
    When the Tie tool is the chosen tool, the mouse buttons have the following function in the cube viewports
                of the main qnet window:
    </p>
    <pre>

                Left Button:  Modify the closest control point
                Middle Button:  Delete the closest control point
                Right Button:  Create new control point

    </pre>
    <p>
        If modifying or creating a point, the Point Editor dialog will be displayed, which will display the
        cube that is the "Reference" cube on the left and the next cube in the control point on the right.
        Only the control measure on the right hand side can be moved.  The measure can be adjusted by:
    </p>
    <pre>

                       1)  clicking the left mouse button will move that cursor position under the crosshair
                       2)  move 1 pixel at a time using arrow keys on the keyboard
                       3)  move 1 pixel at a time using arrow buttons on the Point Editor dialog

        Other Point Editor functions / options:

               Geom:  Geom the right view to match the left view

               Rotate:  Rotate the right view
    
               Blink controls (buttons below left view):  Blink the left and right view in the left view window.
                             Using the arrow keys to move the right view will update the blinking in real time.
    
               Find:   Center the right view so that the same latitude / longitude is under the crosshair as
                          the left view.

               Register:  Sub-pixel register the the right view to the left view.

               Save Point:  Save the control measure under the right view in the control network.

               Add Measure(s) to Point:  Add control measure(s) to the current control point.
               
                        
    </pre>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson, Elizabeth Miller, Stuart Sides, Tracie Sucharski" date="2006-11-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-23">
      Added to Control Networks category
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
