<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="autoseed" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Creates a control network for a list of images
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      <div style="background-color:gold; border:2pxsolidred; fort-weight:bold;">
        This program is being released for a very specific purpose for which it seems to work.
        It is only a preliminary version, and most likely contains errors. It is not ready for general 
        purpose use. Please do not report errors. The documentation is not complete and may
        be inaccurate. USE AT YOUR OWN RISK.
      </div>
    </p>
    <p>
      This program creates a first guess control network with tie points between
      overlapping images. The control network is based on the available pointing information
      for each image (most likely SPICE).
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-08-20">
      Original version
    </change>

    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-27">
      Changed category from Geometry to Control Networks
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of Input cubes to create a control network for
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename which contains a list of
          cube filename to be used to create the control network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SEEDDEF">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          PVL file containing the description of the autoseed plugin
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename which contains the
          definition of the type of autoseeding to be preformed. This file
          must contain a valid Autoseed plugin definition in PVL format.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.api
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the autoseeded control network
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Control">
      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            Name of this control network
        </brief>
        <description>
            The ID or name of this particular control network. This string
            should be unique.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            The pattern to be used to create point ids.
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string with one and only one set of question marks ("?").
            This string will be used to create unique IDs for each control
            point created by this program. The question marks will be replaced
            with a number beginning with zero. For example the pattern
            "User????" would create point IDs "User0001" through 
            "User9999". Note: Make sure there are enough "?"s for all the control
            points that may be created during this run. If all question marks are
            exausted the program will throw an error.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            The description of the network.
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string describing purpose of this control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
